Welcome, students, to Part 2,
Supplemental Video
Review, Pharmacology of
Diuretic Agents. Dr.
Goldstein speaking.
We'll talk about the
thiazide diuretics.
How do thiazide
diuretics reduce blood
pressure for the
management of hypertension?
What is the mechanism
for the use of thiazide
diuretics in the treatment
of vasopressin resistance?
which is also known as
nephrogenic diabetes
insipidus, including
lithium-induced AVP-R.
And what is the mechanism
for the thiazide diuretic's
calcium-preserving
effects? So, hypertension.
Attention, thiazides
acutely lower blood pressure
by reducing extracellular
fluid and the
effective circulating
volume and cardiac output.
Sustained effect is due to
chronic sodium depletion
that decreases vascular
smooth muscle responsiveness
to vasoconstrictors,
leading to the sustained
reduction in peripheral
vascular resistance.
What is the mechanism
for treatment
of vasopressin resistance?
And this is the one that just
seems so counterintuitive.
But if you think about
it, it makes sense. Next,
thiazide-induced mild
volume contraction,
remembering that it
reduces the extracellular
fluid, the effect of
circulating volume,
will cause RAS activation
and decrease GFR.
And that will, in turn,
cause sodium and water
reabsorption in the
proximal tubule. So that
will cause a substantial
drop in filtrate
reaching the vasopressin
-sensitive sites in
the collecting ducts.
Therefore, overall urine
output decreases by
30 to 50 percent. That's
a considerable amount.
So over time, a new lower
steady state is established.
Therefore, urine output
remains chronically
lower than baseline as
long as the drug is taken.
And this effect
works best with the
long-acting thiazide,
chlorothalidone.
Oh,
and this one now. Treatment of
vasopressin resistance
lithium-induced.
It's also used for that.
Discontinue lithium if
the patient is taking
it, and therefore
use the thiazide, low
-sodium diet, low-protein
diet, and an NSAID.
Now, if the patient
needs to continue
lithium, we'll talk
about that when we get to
the epithelial sodium
channel inhibitors.
calcium preserving effects
blocking the NCC in
the distal convoluted
tubule lowers intracellular
sodium concentration
that makes sense and that
will enhance the activity
of the basolateral sodium
calcium exchanger type
1 and that will create
a stronger intracellular
gradient for calcium.
And therefore,
calcium will enter
the cell via the TRPV5 channel.
And the calcium that enters
will bind to calbindin and
then pass through the
epithelial cell and be exported
out via the basolateral NCX1.
That's the main mechanism.
This PMCA1B type of channel,
sorry, pump, is a fine
-tuner. So it's definitely
not the primary mechanism.
Potassium wasting
effect and hyponatremia
and metabolic alkalosis.
These are mechanisms
you need to know. See
if you can remember.
Blocking the NCC and
the DCT increases
sodium and water delivery
to the collecting
ducts. Yes, we've
said this many times.
Delivery of an increased
sodium load to the aldosterone
sensitive sites in the
distal nephron along with
volume contraction causing
aldosterone to be present
upregulates the epithelial
sodium channel, the
sodium ATPase, and also
the ROMK potassium channel,
that's going to
enhance the lumen, the
reabsorption of sodium
through the ENAC is going
to enhance the lumen
negative potential,
and that will favor
potassium to move
out of the cell
and into the lumen.
Therefore, potassium
will be lost,
the potassium wasting effect.
In terms of alkalosis,
The potassium loss leads
to hypokalemia, and
there's increased hydrogen
secretion at the same
time. This is an
aldosterone-related effect.
EC volume contraction, RAS
activation, and therefore
hypokalemic metabolic
alkalosis. And hypochloremia,
because chloride gets
excreted as well, with
bicarbonate retention,
sustained metabolic alkalosis.
and hyponatremia by thiazides.
Thiazide diuretics
impair the kidney's
ability to dilute
urine while the
concentrating ability
remains intact.
Therefore, retention of
water becomes greater than
retention of sodium, so
dilutional hyponatremia. So how
does this happen? The NCC
inhibition impairs urine
dilution because remembering
that the distal convoluted
tubule is impermeable to
water and sodium and chloride
are reabsorbed there in
the distal convoluted
tubule. So blocking it decreases
sodium chloride reabsorption,
increasing the amount
of solutes in the fluid.
And therefore, because
they're solute in the
fluid, then solute-free
water can't be excreted.
Urine concentrating ability
is preserved because
the distal convoluted
tubule has no function in
terms of creating the
medullary gradient or changing
it in any way. So the
medullary gradient
remains intact and the
collecting duct responds to
vasopressin, ADH, antidiuretic
hormone. Therefore
the AQPT aquaporin channels
are inserted into the
collecting ducts and
free water is reabsorbed.
And patients may drink too much
fluid also. They
may feel thirsty.
So, that further adds to the
amount of fluid in the system.
Fortunately, most
patients do not develop
hyponatremia unless water
excretion is impaired.
Insulin resistance, what
is the mechanism? um
the how do why do we use
thiazide diuretic i mean
sorry why does the
thiazide diuretic reduce
speak i'll just read it
how does thiazide diuretic
therapy increase the
risk of lithium toxicity
in patients who are taking
lithium and what about
digoxin toxicity and
what about probandacid.
I'm sure you can see by now
that all of this relates
to the mechanism of action
of the drugs and the
compensatory physiologic
responses. So in terms of
insulin resistance, Well,
think about it this way.
The endocrine pancreas
beta cells store insulin.
When glucose is present,
glucose will enter the
cell, will activate a
series, a cascade of events,
and one of those events is
an ATP-sensitive potassium
channel that will depolarize
and signal calcium channel
to open, and that will
in turn signal release of
insulin. So, focusing on this
ATP-sensitive potassium channel
and thinking now about
hypokalemia, low potassium.
Potassium is needed
in this process of
insulin release,
and when it's low,
it's going to impair
insulin release.
Plus,
thiazides reduce tissue
utilization of glucose, and
that's called impaired
insulin sensitivity, and
that whole thing can lead
to hyperglycemia. This
mechanism here is the major
mechanism of hyperglycemia,
which is not to say
the other one doesn't
count. It does. It
contributes. attributes.
How does size eye
diuretic therapy increase
the risk of lithium
toxicity? Okay.
Well, blocking the NCC, this is
back to our
compensatory effects.
Decreased ineffective
circulating volume,
compensatory reabsorption
of sodium and lithium in the
proximal tubule. Oh,
lithium? Why is lithium
being reabsorbed? Because
lithium uses sodium channels
and so lithium will
be reabsorbed if it's
present there and it will
go into the bloodstream.
Increased plasma levels
of lithium can lead to
lithium toxicity. Why?
Because lithium has a very
narrow therapeutic window
so even a small amount of
increase in the plasma
levels can lead to toxicity.
Digitoxicity, well, it
relates to hypokalemia again.
I put the mechanism
here to help you kind
of visualize what
we're talking about.
so digoxin actually will is
a competitor with potassium
at the sodium potassium
ATPase in cardiomyocytes so
potassium will bind there
to the extracellular region
potassium potassium binding
region and that will
increase the amount of calcium
within the cell, and that
will cause a stronger
contraction. So that's the basic
idea of the clinical use
of digoxin. Now, when serum
potassium is low, lower
amount of potassium, then we
get a greater amount of
the digoxin binding to the
cardiomyocytes, a stronger
inhibition by digoxin. And
that can lead to toxicity,
that can lead to arrhythmia.
Probenicid, well what do
we use Probenicid for?
Probenicid is specifically
designed to inhibit
organic anion transporters
in the kidney. It
was designed to be a
gout drug to prevent uric
acid from flowing back
out into the bloodstream.
Well, it will also prevent
anything that uses organic
anion transporters to be
secreted into the lumen.
So it's a potent inhibitor
of OATs, diuretics,
including thiazide diuretics,
and to the nephron,
predominantly via the OATs.
So blocking them will reduce
the concentration of the
drug at the site of action
within the nephron,
reducing diuretic efficacy.
What are the effects of
concomitant NSAID and
thiazide diuretic on
electrolytes and blood pressure?
As you have seen, I'm
bringing this up over
and over and over. That
is how important it is.
NSAIDs reduce the blood
pressure lowering effective
thiazides by basal
constriction of the
efferent arterial which
lowers renal blood flow which
lowers glomerular
filtration pressure which
lowers glomerular filtration
rate which decreases
the amount of anything
that gets filtered into
the nephron. In addition,
it lowers the amount
of drug that's passing
through the glomerulus
around to the paratubular
capillaries to the organic
anion transporters. So
that amount is lower on
top of the fact that
NSAIDs will block the OAT.
Plus, NSAIDs increase
sodium and water
reabsorption
upstream of the NCCs.
What are the clinical and
mechanistic rationales
for using thiazide diuretic
with a loop diuretic?
And it's all about
edema. Reduction of
edema by sequential
nephron blockade for
synergistic natriuretic
diuretic effect.
Loop diuretics block
sodium reabsorption in the
NKCC2 in the thick
ascending limb. Some of the
sodium is reabsorbed at
distal sites in the nephron,
including the NCC. So
thiazides block that.
So sequential block,
therefore preventing
reabsorption of
sodium there. It's a
much bigger natriuretic
-diuretic effect.
A 58-year-old female newly
diagnosed with primary
hypertension has started on
hydrochlorothiazide. At follow
-up four weeks later, her
blood pressure has improved.
She reports that she's
been trying to follow
the dietary advice but
admits to consuming
salted popcorn every
afternoon. So tempting.
Routine laboratory testing
reveals serum potassium
3.1 and I've given you
a normal range there.
which was previously normal.
She denies muscle
weakness and palpitations.
What is the cause of
the decreased potassium?
Thiazides increase
distal sodium delivery.
Higher sodium intake
increases distal sodium
delivery, leading to
increased epithelial
sodium channel-mediated
sodium reabsorption of
potassium secretion,
resulting in hypokalemia.
And now our epithelial
sodium channel inhibitors.
Ameloride is the main one.
The one that I've
starred, I believe
it's the most frequently
used one also.
And the mineralocorticoid
receptor
antagonists. We think
of them together because
they're both potassium
-sparing diuretics.
Why are ENAC inhibitors and MR
antagonists referred
to as weak diuretics?
Because only a small amount
of sodium reaches that
part of the nephron, so only
a small amount of sodium
gets blocked by these two
drugs, two types of drugs.
Therefore, epithelial
sodium channel
inhibitors and MR
antagonists will block only
a small fraction of
the total sodium,
thus water, and that's
it. So small amount of
natriuresis, diuresis. How
do the mechanisms of action
of the ENAC inhibitors
and MR antagonists differ?
We talk about potassium
sparing effect,
so how are they different?
Epithelial sodium channel
inhibitors block sodium
reabsorption through
the luminal epithelial
sodium channels. MR
antagonists pass through the
basolateral membrane,
block the mineralocorticoid
receptor, and the
cytosol pretty much the
same way as we've learned
about how cortisol does
it. Both of these drugs
are corticosteroids.
The MR and drug complex
translocates to the nucleus,
binds specific response
elements in the DNA, which
stimulates transcription
and expression of various
genes involved in the
sodium reabsorption and
potassium excretion. So we've
already talked about several
times the aldosterone
-sensitive sites, upregulation
of ENAC, increased activity
of the sodium-potassium
ATPase, increased
activity of the ROMK, and
hydrogen secretion from the
type A intercalated cells.
blocking either side of action
reduces sodium absorption
increases sodium excretion
followed by water
natriuresis and diuresis and
what is the mechanism for the
potassium sparing effect
it's going to be just the
opposite of what we saw with
the potassium losing effect
we're blocking the
epithelial sodium
channel therefore
sodium is not flowing in
Therefore,
the lumen-negative
potential difference is
abolished, and that's
going to reduce the
electrochemical
gradient for potassium.
So potassium is retained, and
that can lead to hyperkalemia.
And what is the
role of these drugs
in the management
of hypertension?
Well,
they're combined
with the thiazides
frequently to
counteract the potassium
wasting effect of the
thiazide diuretic.
And also, they still do
block sodium reabsorption
distal to the NCC, which
will increase the effect.
What other drugs increase
the risk of hyperkalemia
when administered with
the ENAC inhibitor
or the mineralocorticoid
receptor antagonist.
And I'm sure you can,
this is intuitive.
I'm sure you've
figured this one out.
So ACE inhibitors
and ARBs and direct
renin inhibitors, those are RAS
inhibitors. They are
potassium retaining
because of the reduction
in aldosterone.
NSAIDs, talked about
that a bunch of times.
Potassium supplements in the
diet and calcineurin
inhibitors.
So basically,
it's anything that
will increase serum potassium.
Why is an MR antagonist
the recommended drug of
choice for treating ascites
due to hepatic cirrhosis?
This is really an important
concept to remember
for the boards, but
also for practice, and
you should be familiar
with the mechanism.
So let's figure out
what's happening with
ascites first due to
hepatic cirrhosis.
Portal hypertension, because
the liver is fibrosed,
increases hydrostatic
pressure, which leads
to fluid transudation
into the peritoneal
cavity, which contributes
to effective hypovolemia,
reduced effective
circulating volume.
Splankic vasodilation will
occur, and it's triggered
by nitric oxide and other
vasodilators in response to
this portal hypertension,
which will lead to reduced
systemic vascular resistance,
which activates the
sympathetic nervous system
and the renal angiotensin
aldosterone system, and
vasopressin, leading to sodium and
water retention. In addition,
the liver is not functioning
well, so it's not making
albumins, so hypoalbuminemia
due to liver dysfunction
decreases oncotic
pressure, which facilitates fluid
leakage from the capillaries
into the interstitium and
the peritoneal spaces.
Now, why spironolactone?
because the patients
with ascites and hepatic
cirrhosis are in a state
of hyperaldosteronism.
So spironolactone is blocking
the effect of aldosterone.
What is the role of ENAC
inhibitors in lithium
-induced nephrogenic
diabetes insipidus? Well,
we know that these drugs will
block the entry of sodium
through the epithelial
sodium channel, but it also
blocks the entry of lithium
into the principal cells.
So what if lithium enters
the principal cells?
Then what happens?
Well, it gets stuck in
there because it's not
pumped out. We know
sodium gets pumped out,
but lithium doesn't.
So lithium accumulates
in the principal
cells, and that
interferes with the
expression and
trafficking of the AQP2.
And as a result,
water is not reabsorbed.
In other words, the
cells in the collecting
duct are not sensitive
to vasopressin, to
antidiuretic hormone.
Therefore, the collecting
duct becomes impermeable
to water and the
patient gets polyuria.
Polyuria. So by blocking
epithelial sodium
channel that
prevents lithium from
accumulating in there
and that will help reduce
polyuria and the
vasopressin resistance.
why is an enac inhibitor
recommended treatment for
little syndrome well little
syndrome is a rare autosomal
dominant disorder that's a
gain of function mutation
in the genes that regulate
enac so there's more enac
expression a lot more
and if there's more enac
expression there's going to
be more sodium reabsorbed and
therefore more potassium
that's excreted and so on.
So ENAC inhibitor plus
sodium restriction
will manage the
hypertension and the
hypokalemia that's
caused by this disorder.
Why is an MR antagonist
recommended for heart failure
with reduced or preserved
ejection fraction in
patients who are already
stabilized on therapy? And
that's because of the
evidence from well-designed
randomized clinical trials
that spironolactone, in
conjunction with standard
therapy in patients who are
at low risk for hyperkalemia,
will improve outcomes.
What are the mechanistic
and clinical rationales
for treating acne in
females with spironolactone?
Well, spironolactone has
anti-androgenic effects
because it will block androgen
receptors and it will also
inhibit testosterone
synthesis, which in turn shifts
the estrogen-testosterone
balance towards estrogen.
And the point being,
it's blocking androgen
receptors and that's
going to help the acne.
A 70-year-old woman with
hypertension is treated
with hydrochlorothiazide
and spironolactone. After
beginning daily naproxen
for knee pain, her labs show
rising creatinine and
potassium level, 5.8
milliequivalents, which is
dangerously high. Of course, she
would have taken this on
her own. It would not have
been prescribed by a doctor
who would know better,
and naproxen is readily
available over-the-counter.
It's advertised on television.
It's talked about by friends.
It makes sense that people
would use it on their own.
Explain the mechanism
of the drug-drug
interaction leading to
this adverse drug event.
Well, this is
another triple hit.
Thiazides reduce the
effect of circulating
volume, decrease renal
perfusion pressure, therefore
compensatory mechanisms
maintain GFR, including
prostaglandin-mediated
afferent dilation.
NSAIDs block the afferent
arterial dilation.
Constriction occurs,
decreases renal blood flow,
reduces GFR, and so on.
Thiazides plus NSAID
together causes a marked
reduction in GFR,
which decreases serum
creatinine and risks
acute kidney injury.
Spironolactone decreases
enact activity and
sodium reabsorption,
removing the lumen negative
potential, therefore
decreasing potassium
secretion via ROMK, and
potassium gets retained.
And NSAIDs cause retention
of potassium, and they
are inhibitory on ADH
thus kidney injury we'll
talk about the osmotic
diuretics now I found this
picture I hope it
helps you this is from
creativemeddoses.com and the
artist is Priyanka Singh.
What is the primary mechanism
of action of mannitol?
What parts of the nephron
is primarily affected by
mannitol? What is mannitol's
primary therapeutic use?
So let's get to it.
Mannitol is a sugar alcohol
and other osmotic diuretics
will increase the
concentration of solutes in the
plasma and interstitial
spaces in the renal tubules.
It is not reabsorbed
in the renal tubules.
The elevated osmolarity
produces an osmotic gradient
which draws water from areas
of lower solute concentration
like brain parenchyma and
eye and cells into the
plasma and interstitial
fluid and the renal tubules.
The water is excreted as
urine. So, what parts of
the nephron are primarily
affected by mannitol? In other
words, what parts will
allow water to be drawn in?
The proximal tubule
and descending limb
of the loop of Henle
are permeable to
water. and that's where
water is drawn in.
Also, mannitol impairs
water reabsorption in the
collecting tubule because of
that high osmotic pressure.
Water is not going to be,
well, it's unfavorable for
the passive diffusion of water
through aquaporins should
they be present into the
medullary area. What is
mannitol's primary therapeutic
use? Intracranial pressure
relief. By increasing solute
concentration in plasma,
mannitol osmatically draws
water out of the brain
parenchyma into the intravascular
space, reducing ICP,
and then the water is
excreted. Intraocular pressure
by the same mechanism,
mannitol induces, reduces IOP
in acute emergencies where
rapid IOP reduction is
critical. It's not going to
be used as a regular thing.
And mannitol is
given by bolus doses.
It's not given by
continuous infusion.
What is a potential serious
adverse effect of mannitol?
Volume expansion, leading
to pulmonary edema
in patients with left
-sided heart failure as
fluid overload causes the
fluid back up into the
lungs, increasing pulmonary
capillary pressure,
causing leakage into
the alveolar spaces.
Volume expansion causes
electrolyte imbalance with
hyponatremia due to the fluid
overload or hypernatremia
if dehydration results
from the use of this.
Profound diuresis causing
fluid and electrolyte loss.
So what is happening
with electrolytes? They
just get dragged along
with the fluid. Why is
mannitol contraindicated
in patients with anuria?
Well, if the patient
is not making urine,
then the mannitol is
going to accumulate
in the extracellular
fluid, volume overload,
pulmonary edema,
hypertensive crisis,
hypertensive
encephalopathy, renal
failure. Must be very careful.
Pharmacokinetic properties.
Well, it's administered
IV, rapidly distributes
to the extracellular
compartment, freely
filtered by the
glomerulus, minimal
reabsorption, onset of ICP
reduction pretty quickly,
but the duration can
be up to six hours.
A 65-year-old male is admitted
for treatment of traumatic
brain injury and elevated
intracranial pressure.
He is treated with intravenous
mannitol, resulting
in initial improvement in
neurologic status. Several
hours later, he develops
acute shortness of breath,
crackles on lung exam, and
decreased oxygen saturation.
Chest imaging reveals
bilateral pulmonary
edema, and the mechanism
is osmotic gradient
pulls water from the
intracellular to the
interstitial to the
intravascular compartment,
causing rapid expansion
of plasma volume.
Increased intravascular
volume increases the venous
return to the heart,
which is going to increase
preload, which increases
pulmonary capillary pressure.
High hydrostatic
pressure in the pulmonary
capillaries pushes fluid
into the lung tissue,
causing pulmonary
edema. And risk factors,
patients with heart
failure, renal impairment,
existing volume, overload,
because they just
simply cannot handle all
of this extra volume.
And that concludes
the questions.
Here's a little mind
map of the diuretics,
if you find mind
maps to be helpful.
They're usually most helpful
when we make them ourselves.
And I've put the summary
in as brief a way as I can.
Hopefully it'll help
you to remember what
the key points of
diuretic therapy are.
And I've given you NSAIDs.
NSAIDs, interactions
and effects. And
hopefully this will help
you remember what the
NSAIDs are doing in
each of these various
situations. various
drug-drug interactions.
And another table to try
and help you organize.
And that's it and we
have our questions,
question answers. That
concludes the series on
the diuretic therapy.